DAIPAYAN SARKAR

Molecular Dynamics | Computational Biophysics | Thermodynamics | Chemical Kinetics | Free-Energy Methods | Enhanced Sampling | Cryo-EM

- @ sarkarda@msu.edu
- East Lansing, MI, USA 0000-0002-4167-2108
- **J** 214-385-9383 @17Dsarkar
- 612 Wilson Rd. East Lansing, MI 48824 in daipayansarkar
 - daipayans
- G Google Scholar: Daipayan Sarkar



EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Scientist

MSU-DOE Plant Research Laboratory

May 2021 -

• Using molecular dynamics (MD) simulations, we are collaborating with a team of experimental researchers to develop novel ways to engineer bacterial microcompartments. Toward these molecular simulations, we provide a mechanistic view of the thermodynamics (free energy) and kinetics (mean passage time) for transport of small photosynthetic metabolites across bacterial microcompartments such as carboxysomes found in cyanobacteria.

Postdoctoral Research Associate

Department of Biological Sciences, Purdue University

July 2019 - Apr 2021

West Lafayette, IN

- Using shape complementarity algorithm for protein-protein interactions, specifically for membrane proteins, for the challenge of CAPRI protein binding.
- Protein structure refinement using molecular dynamics and enhanced sampling (Gaussian Accerelated MD, Metadynamics) to improve the quality of predicted structures, predicted using a deep learning-based algorithm in the CASP14.
- Cryo-EM protein structure refinement and ligand challenge to flexibly fit protein structures and ligand in EM density maps for EMChallenge2021.
- Quantifying protein (OCRL1) conformational change and quantify lipid interactions due to mutations occurring in Lowe syndrome.

Postdoctoral Research Associate

Department of Mechanical Engineering, University of Texas, Dallas

June 2017 – June 2019

Richardson, TX

• A chemical kinetic (reaction- diffusion) model was used to determine the rate of temperature-dependent plasmonic protein inactivation. The concept developed has been extended to major applications in areas of targeted drug delivery and diffusion across the blood-brain barrier.

Adjunct Lecturer

Department of Mechanical Engineering, University of Texas, Arlington

i Jan 2017 - May 2017

Linux, HPC (Slurm, Torque)

Arlington, TX

Taught the undergraduate course in the fundamentals of thermodynamics, chemical kinetics, and heat transfer.

SOFTWARE SKILLS

Molecular Dynamics - NAMD, GROMACS, VMD Free Energy calculations (REUS, ABF), FEP Enhanced sampling (GAMD, Metadynamics) QM - Single point energy, Optimization (Gaussian16) Python, Tcl, Bash, MATLAB Docking: Autodock-Vina, RosettaDock, HADDOCK Structure prediction: BLAST, Modeller, AlphaFold ROSETTA, UCSF Chimera, Phenix

HIGHLIGHTS

Cryo-EM structure of AztraZeneca COVID-19 viral vector, ChAdOx1 (PDB: 7RD1)

We used molecular dynamics and cryo-EM density to flexibly fit protein subunits into the density map. Using state-of-the-art molecular simulations and SPR experiments, the data confirmed that the PF4 protein is capable of forming stable complexes with clinically relevant adenoviruses, an important step in unraveling the mechanisms underlying the thrombocytopenia syndrome. This work was published in Science Advances and was highlighted worldwide in media platforms such as BBC, EurekAlert (AAAS), to name a few.

ISPR-DOE award for 18th International Photosynthesis Congress in Dunedin, New Zealand

This award was awarded to present my current research on the transport of photosynthetic metabolites (or substrates) across bacterial microcompartments. This research aims at providing a mechanistic view of the per meability of small molecules across microcompartments and determining the rate-limiting step of the transport of these photosynthetic compounds. Research can be applied to sustainable, metabolic and bioengineering applications.



Doctoral Dissertation Fellowship

Awarded annually by College of Engineering, University of Texas at Arlington, to select PhD students for outstanding research.

STRENGTHS

Hard-working

Fast-learner

Research, Creativity & Problem Solving

Self-motivated & Leader

Teamwork & Mentorship

Communication Skills

Technical Writing & Presentations

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Mechanical Engineering University of Texas, Arlington, USA

Aug 2012 - Aug 2016

M.S. Mechanical Engineering University of Texas, Arlington, USA

Aug 2010 - May 2012

B.Eng. Mechanical Engineering University of Mumbai, India

May 2006 - May 2010

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Journal Articles

- Gupta, C., Sarkar, D., Tieleman, D. P., & Singharoy, A. (2022). The ugly, bad, and good stories of large-scale biomolecular simulations. *Current Opinion in Structural Biology*, 73, 102338. doi:10.1016/j.sbi.2022.102338
- Vant, J. W., Sarkar, D., Nguyen, J., Baker, A. T., Vermaas, J. V., & Singharoy, A. (2022). Exploring cryo-electron microscopy with molecular dynamics. *Biochemical Society Transactions*, 50(1), 569–581. doi:10.1042/BST20210485
- Baker, A. T., Boyd, R. J., Sarkar, D., Teijeira-Crespo, A., Chan, C. K., ... Borad, M. J. (2021). ChAdOx1 interacts with CAR and PF4 with implications for thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndrome. *Science Advances*, 7(49), eabl8213. doi:10. 1126/sciadv.abl8213
- Lawson, C. L., Kryshtafovych, A., Adams, P. D., Afonine, P. V., Baker, M. L., ...
 Chiu, W. (2021). Cryo-EM model validation recommendations based on outcomes of the 2019 EMDataResource challenge. *Nature Methods*, 18(2), 156–164. doi:10.1038/s41592-020-01051-w
- Lensink, M. F., Brysbaert, G., Mauri, T., Nadzirin, N., Velankar, S., ... Wodak, S. J. (2021). Prediction of protein assemblies, the next frontier: The CASP14-CAPRI experiment. Proteins: Structure, Function, and Bioinformatics, 89(12), 1800–1823. doi:10.1002/prot.26222
- Shekhar, M., Terashi, G., Gupta, C., Sarkar, D., Debussche, G., ... Singharoy, A. (2021). CryoFold: Determining protein structures and data-guided ensembles from cryo-EM density maps. *Matter*, 4(10), 3195–3216. doi:10.1016/j.matt. 2021.09.004
- Aderinwale, T., Christoffer, C. W., Sarkar, D., Alnabati, E., & Kihara, D. (2020).
 Computational structure modeling for diverse categories of macromolecular interactions. *Current Opinion in Structural Biology*, 64, 1–8. doi:10.1016/j.sbi. 2020.05.017
- Vant, J. W., Lahey, S.-L. J., Jana, K., Shekhar, M., Sarkar, D., ... Singharoy, A. (2020). Flexible Fitting of Small Molecules into Electron Microscopy Maps Using Molecular Dynamics Simulations with Neural Network Potentials. *Journal of Chemical Information and Modeling*, 60(5), 2591–2604. doi:10.1021/acs.jcim. 9b01167
- Vant, J. W., Sarkar, D., Streitwieser, E., Fiorin, G., Skeel, R., ... Singharoy, A. (2020). Data-guided Multi-Map variables for ensemble refinement of molecular movies. The Journal of Chemical Physics, 153(21), 214102. doi:10.1063/5. 0022433
- Sarkar, D., Kang, P., Nielsen, S. O., & Qin, Z. (2019). Non-Arrhenius Reaction-Diffusion Kinetics for Protein Inactivation over a Large Temperature Range. ACS Nano, 13(8), 8669–8679. doi:10.1021/acsnano.9b00068
- Sarkar, D., Haji-Sheikh, A., & Jain, A. (2015). Temperature distribution in multilayer skin tissue in presence of a tumor. *International Journal of Heat and Mass Transfer*, 91, 602–610. doi:10.1016/j.ijheatmasstransfer.2015.07.089

Conference Proceedings

- Doole, F. T., Chan, C. K., Streitwieser, E., Sarkar, D., Struts, A. V., ... Brown, M. F. (2022). Rivalry of cholesterol and antimicrobial peptides as seen by molecular simulations and NMR spectroscopy. In *Biophysical Journal* (Vol. 121, 161a–162a). doi:10.1016/j.bpj.2021.11.1922
- Sarkar, D., Egelston, J. L., & Vermaas, J. V. (2022). Correlating the transport cycle
 of small multidrug resistance transporters. In *Biophysical Journal* (Vol. 121, 393a–
 394a). doi:10.1016/j.bpj.2021.11.800
- Doole, F. T., Chan, C. K., Streitwieser, E., Sarkar, D., Kim, M., ... Brown, M. F. (2021). Antimicrobial Peptide-Membrane Interactions: Insights from Molecular Simulations. In *Biophysical Journal* (Vol. 120, 141a). doi:10.1016/j.bpj.2020.11. 1052

Pre-prints

- Sarkar, D., Santiago, I., & Vermaas, J. (2022). Atomistic Origins of Biomass Recalcitrance in Organosolv Pretreatment. doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2022-9j7zv
- Sarkar, D., Lee, H., Vant, J. W., Turilli, M., Jha, S., & Singharoy, A. (2021). Scalable Adaptive Protein Ensemble Refinement Integrating Flexible Fitting. doi:10.1101/ 2021.12.07.471672

*For a complete record of all publications, refer to my google scholar on page 1.

REFEREES

Dr. Josh Vermaas

@ Michigan State University

✓ vermassj@msu.edu

Assistant Professor MSU-DOE Plant Research Laboratory 1130 Molecular Plant Sciences East Lansing, MI 48824 Association: Postdoc Advisor

Dr. Abhishek Singharoy

@ Arizona State University

 ■ asinghar@asu.edu

Assistant Professor School of Molecular Sciences Tempe, AZ 85287-1604 Association: Scientific collaborator (since 2017) and supervisor for AstraZeneca COVID-19 vaccine work.

Dr. Ankur Jain

The University of Texas at Arlington

Associate Professor

Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, Bioengineering (affiliated) 500 W 1st St

Arlington, TX 76010

Association: Ph.D. supervisor

Dr. Zhenpeng Qin

The University of Texas at Dallas

Associate Professor

Department of Mechanical Engineering Department of Bioengineering Department of Surgery (University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center) 800 West Campbell Rd. Richardson, TX 75080-3021

Association: Advisor

SYNERGISTIC SCIENCE

